Preliminary Inventory of the Racho Petrov Papers, 1885-1916
Hoover Institution Archives
Racho Petrov Papers,
1885-1916
82051
Petrov, Racho
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, dispatches, orders, and reports, relating to political, military, and diplomatic affairs in Bulgaria, Bulgarian participation in World War I, and the suppression of an attempted military coup in Bulgaria in 1886.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Bulgaria.; Bulgaria.; Bulgaria--History--1878-1944.; Bulgarian Review Center.
Container List
- During the reign of Prince Battenberg (Box 1)
  - A letter from the War Ministry to Captain Racho Petroff, 1885 April 22, written in Russian, the high positions in the Ministry being still in the hands of Russian officers. The letter deals with the establishment of military camps near the principal towns (2 documents) (#1, in original Russian)
  - An order issued by the War Ministry to Captain Racho Petroff to join the Regiment of Strouma, 1885 September 9, Bulgarian-Serbian War. A second order cancelling the first, requesting Captain Racho Petroff to present himself to the Head of State - Prince Battenberg at Plovdiv (2 documents) (#2, in original Russian)
  - Pro-memoria written by Major Groueff, requesting some appointments in the Army, dated 1886 February 10, remitted to Major Racho Petroff by D. Petcoff (#3, in original Bulgarian)
  - A letter from Vinaroff to Groueff, 1886 August 11, both high ranking officers, preparing the coup d'état against the Prince (#4, in original Bulgarian)
  - A letter from A. Ouzounoff to Racho Petroff, Bucarest, 1886 May 30, regarding the delimitation of the Bulgarian-Rumanian border. Only a few months later Uouzounoff as head of the military mutiny in Roussé will be condemned to death and executed (#5, in original Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to Captain Paprikoff, 1886, referring to the activities of the Russian General Kaulbars in Bulgaria (#6, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Captain Ouvaliev to Major Racho Petroff, 1886, on the same subject (#7, in Bulgarian)
  - Order given by Col. Mutkuroff (future Regent) to Major Racho Petroff to accompany the Prince of Battenberg in his trip to Northern Bulgaria, 1888 April 12 (#8, in original Bulgarian)
  - Diploma signed by Prince Alexander of Battenberg, granting Captain Racho Petroff a high decoration, 1885 November 29 (#8a, in original Bulgarian)
- During the reign of Prince Ferdinand of Cobourg-Saxe-Gotha
  - A letter from Prince Ferdinand to Colonel Racho Petroff, February 28, on whether a mass for the memory of the late Emperor Alexander II should be celebrated (#9, manuscript in French and Bulgarian)
  - Full powers to Col. Racho Petroff, Chief of Staff of the Bulgarian Army to preside the Bulgarian-Turkish commission for delimitating the frontier, 1891 May 20 (10, in original French)
  - A letter from Prince Ferdinand to Col. Racho Petroff, ordering the immediate nomination of a lieutenant, 1893 May 29 (#11, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from Prince Ferdinand to Col. Racho Petroff, granting him a high decoration, 1890 August 3 (#12, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A note from Prince Ferdinand to Col. Racho Petroff, asking to explain some state expenses, 1893 November 3 (#13, manuscript in French)
  - A note from Prince Ferdinand to Col. Racho Petroff, requesting that Captain Athanassoff take military oath, sent probably after the death of Princess Marie-Louise, 1889 (#14, manuscript in French)
  - Two reports from Racho Petroff, Minister of Interior, to Prince Ferdinand, soliciting the Prince to nominate two heads of districts, 1890 December 7 (#15, in original Bulgarian)
  - Letter from Racho Petroff, Chief of the General Staff to Prince Ferdinand, on a supposed attempt of murder, 1891 December 26 (#16, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A copy of the newspaper Bulgaria, 1901 January 11 - leading paper of the Liberal Progressiste Party (Dr. Stoyan Daneff) sent by the Prince Ferdinand to General Racho Petroff, Minister of Interior (#17)
  - A letter from the Secret Cabinet of H. R. H. the Prince to Minister Racho Petroff, requesting the restitution of 5.000 levas advanced personally by the Prince to cover the expenses of the delegation sent to the funerals of Queen Victoria, 1901 January 19 (#18, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from leaders of the opposition parties sent to Prince Ferdinand, protesting against some irregularities in connection with the next elections, 1901, with a note written by Racho Petroff (2 documents) (#19, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from the Bulgarian Diplomatic Agent in Constantinople Ivan S. Gueshoff to Prime Minister Ivantchev, 1901 January 9-22, to pay an informant (#20, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Politische Korrespondenz, 1901 January 13, the fall of Ivanchov's Cabinet, and Racho Petroff's rising (#21)
  - Copy of a proclamation by Prince Ferdinand, before going to London for the celebration of Queen Victoria, 1901 (#22, copy in Bulgarian)
  - Cable from Minister Racho Petroff to Prince Ferdinand, asking authorization to dissolve the municipal council of Dupnitza, no date (#23, original in Bulgarian)
  - An anonymous letter sent to the Palace in Sofia with critics against the Prince and "King Petroff", Pleven, 1901 January 13 (#24, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - An Ukaze, signed by the Prince, nominating a new municipal councilor in Plovdiv, 1901 January (#25, original in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from Prince Ferdinand to Lt. Col. Racho Petroff, menacing to take strong measures if the discipline among the officers of his Escort is not immediately restored, no date (#26, manuscript in French)
  - Cables sent by Ministers Natchovitch and Stoilov in connection with the present ministerial crisis, 1895 August 25 (#27, original in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from D. Petcoff (father of Nicholas Petcoff, assassinated by the communists in Sofia in 1947,) Minister of Interior to General Racho Petroff, Prime Minister, requesting measures to impede any crossing of the border by Macedonian "tcheti", 1901 September 19 (#28, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A letter sent by Gal. Racho Petroff as Minister of Foreign Affairs to D. Mintchovitch, Bulgarian Diplomatic Agent in Rome, examining the international situation and especially the Macedonian Question, 1904 February 15 (#29, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Note about a clash between socialists (Sakazov) and Macedonians at a political rally in Sofia, 1903 June 1 (#30, original in Bulgarian)
  - Copy of a letter sent by General Racho Petroff to the Prince, dealing with some promotions in the Army, no date (#31, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Order to pay indemnities to refugees from Macedonia and the district of Andrinople (after the Iliden insurrection, 1903,) 1904 February 7 (#32, original in Bulgarian)
  - Notes written by Vernazza from the palace on the draft of a Commercial Convention with Turkey, 1904 July 21 (3 documents) (#33, manuscript in French)
  - A cable from Marienbad, the Prince requests the presence of General Racho Petroff, no date (#34, original in Bulgarian)
  - The Prince invites Gal. Petroff to the Palace, no date (#35, Manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - The Prince requests General Racho Petroff to show to Stern Gverazdowski the "Institutions of Artillery" in Sofia, no date (#36, manuscript in French)
  - Cable from Dr. D. Stancioff, Bulgarian Diplomatic Agent in Saint Petersburg to Prince Ferdinand. The leader of the opposition Dragan Tsankov, visits Count Lamsdorf criticizing the government in Sofia, 1903 June 1 (#37, copy in Bulgarian)
  - Two letters from D. Petcov to General Racho Petroff on internal affairs, 1903 June 6,7 (2 documents) (#38, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A rescript of the Prince, sent to Racho Petroff, Prime Minister regarding the celebration of the 7th anniversary of the Crown Prince Boris, born 1901 January 16 (2 documents) (#39, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from Prince Ferdinand to Racho Petroff regarding the Macedonian Question, no date (#40, manuscript in French)
  - A report sent by the Bulgarian Commercial Agent in Andrinople, to D. Petcov, Minister of Interior, 1905 March 26, on the situation of the Bulgarian population in the region - Petcov's commentaries (#41, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Two letters from Mr. Dobrovitch, Councilor of the Prince, one informing that Prince Ferdinand allows Racho Petroff to go to Paris, the other to D. Petcov, Minister of Interior requesting the Cabinet for a meeting (2 documents) (#42, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Austrian and Hungarian newspapers commentaries on the Bulgarian-Serbian Custom Convention, 1905 March 27 (#43, translated in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from D. Petcov to Racho Petroff, The Prince accepts his demission as Prime Minister, 1906 October 24 (#44, Manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Letters from Ivan Stoyanoff - Director General of the Post and Telegraph Department to the Minister of Foreign Affairs, 1905 July 21, Constantinople, on the signature of a Postal Convention with Turkey - "to include or not the Eastern Roumalia as part of the Turkish Empire" (2 documents) (#45, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Letter from the Bulgarian Diplomatic Agent in Cettigné - Montenegro, Andrei Toshev, to Racho Petroff, Minister of Foreign Affairs, 1906 August 9, on a conversation with Count von Cervin on anti-Greek activities in Bulgaria (complaints on life conditions in Cettigné) (#46, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Prince Ferdinand to Racho Petroff, 1905 July 19, the last intends to leave his functions (#47, in Bulgarian)
  - A report from the Bulgarian Diplomatic Agent in Bucarest to Racho Petroff, Minister of Foreign Affairs, 1906 August 15, on the strained relations between Bulgaria and Russia (#48, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A clipping from Politische Korrespondez, Vienna, on "Furst Ferdinand von Bulgarien," no date (#49, in German)
  - Documents referring to the Bulgarian-Turkish Trade and Consular Convention, 1906 (3 documents) (#50, original in Bulgarian)
  - Cables from the Diplomatic Agent in Paris to Racho Petroff, Prime Minister, 1906 January, on Trade Convention between Bulgarian and France - French schools in Bulgaria (9 documents) (#51, in Bulgarian)
  - Cable from Dr. D. I. Stancioff, Diplomatic Agent in St. Petersburg, on some newspapermen's reports from Pirot, unfavourable to Prince Ferdinand, published in Birjevie Vedomosti, no date (#52, in Bulgarian)
  - Cable from Prince Ferdinand to Prime Minister Racho Petroff, not to insist on the word "Eastern Rumalia" but to speed the signing of Convention with Turkey, 1906 July 18, from Munich (#53, in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from Colonel L. Lamouche, French officer in Macedonia European Mission, to General Racho Petroff on the diplomatic crisis between Bulgaria and Turkey, 1909 February 1-13, Salonique (#54, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from N. Vladikin, Paris, to General Racho Petroff, on the Russian Foreign Minister Isvolski's visit in Paris, 1910 February 24 (#55, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from a Bulgarian living in the States, Detroit, 1914 February 2, suggesting to General Racho Petroff the purchase of a large farm in the South West to receive all Bulgarian refugees, especially those from Macedonia (cost: circa 200.000 levas - gold) (#56, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from T. Gatev to General Racho Petroff, about which side Bulgaria should take in the First World War, 1915 August 7 (#57, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A letter sent by the German General F. Unger to Col. Daneff, complaining that the Bulgarian authorities do not allow the remittance of the cattle bought by the German Army in Dobroudja (WWI); 1916 January 15 (#58, copy in German and Bulgarian)
  - A cable to all Bulgarian authorities in Macedonia to allow Germans to send to Germany all the wool bought by them up to this date, 1916 May 15 (#59, in original Bulgarian)
  - General Racho Petroff, this time Governor of Macedonia (WWI), requests for his use a house and a stable occupied by the German troops. The German reply - "Nein", 1916 June 11 (#60, original in Bulgarian and German)
  - Drafts of two reports sent by General Racho Petroff, one from Kustendil about the mission of Lady Piadget in Scopié, and the other from Constanza on some disputes between Bulgarians and Germans in the occupied Dobroudja, 1916 December 9 (#61, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A map of Bulgaria printed in 1914, after the Treaty of Bucarest, 1913 August (#62)
  - A letter from D. Petcov, Minister of Interior to Racho Petroff, Prime Minister, about the coming parliamentary elections, 1903 October 4 (#63, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Cable from the Sultan to the Prince of Bulgaria, appointing him Governor of Eastern Rumalia, 1903 March 15. Letter from Dobrovitch from the palace: "The Ruler found Sultan's cable COLD"-3 documents (#64, in Bulgarian and French)
  - A notice from the Palace (Vernazza) to Racho Petroff, Prime Minister to readmit Kouzmanoff at his post in Serres, no date (#65, manuscript in French)
  - A letter from Abazzia, 1906 October 26 to General Racho Petroff, regrets for his resigning (#66, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Several invitations from the Palace to Racho Petroff to visit the Prince (#67, in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from Vladigueroff, from Shoumene, 1900 December 30 to Racho Petroff, Minister of Interior about how the local Turks could influence the coming elections (#68, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Commentaries written by Racho Petroff on the book written by his ex-wife, Sultana R. P. (sharp critics) (#69, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A note from Prince Ferdinand to Colonel Racho Petroff, 1891 December 25 (#70, manuscript in French)
  - A letter from the Bulgarian Agent in Andrinople, 1903 July 11, to Prime Minister Racho Petroff, recommending the correspondent of Times, London - Lieutenant Howell (#71, manuscript in Bulgarian)
- Military Mutiny in Roussé and Silistra, 1887 - fomented by Tzarist Russia
  - A cable from Captain Paprikoff to the Minister of War, 1886 March 1, on the conspiracy in South Bulgaria against the Government, Tchirpan (#1, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Captain Paprikoff to the Minister of War, 1886 February 28, Stara-Zagora, on the mutiny and executions (#2, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Captain Paprikoff to the Minister of War, 1886 February, Stara-Zagora, on the same subject (#3, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Minister of War (no date), on a meeting with Filov, the head of the mutiny in Roussé (Filov would be executed a short time later) (#4, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to Captain Paprikoff, on the mutiny in Roussé and Silistra (#5, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Captain Nikiforoff to Major Petroff, on an investigation of an alert (#6, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Captain Ivanoff to Captain Ouvalieff on not impeding the investigation (#7, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from major Petroff to Captain Ouvalieff in Shoumen, authorizing the necessary measures (#8, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Petroff to Lieutenant Valnaroff, on orders to send the ship (#9, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Petroff to Captain Drandarevski, on sending the company back to Varna (#10, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Petroff to Captain Ouvaliev, Shoumen, on taking measures against officers under suspicion (#11, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Petroff to Captain Tzontchev, Shoumen, on arresting Vladimir Blaskoff (#12, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Petroff to Captain Drandarewski, Silistra, on liberating Dr. Kazassovitch, requested by the Rumanian Government (#13, In Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Petroff to Captain Paprikoff, on keeping in Roussé a suspected officer (#14, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Petroff to the Minister of War, on an order to the troops from Razgrad to return to their barracks (#15, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Ratchev from the post office in Shoumen to Major Racho Petroff, 1886 September 19 (the note was delivered personally to Captain Parikoff) (#16, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Roussé to Major Racho Petroff, Sofia, asking for instructions how to treat Captain Punayotov (#17, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Commander of the Escort, keeping at his disposal an officer from the Escort (#18, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to Minister Natchovitch and the Minister of War against the activities of the German Consul in Roussé, as representing the interests of Russia (#19, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to Colonel Nicolaef, giving the names of the officers involved in the mutiny, most of them wounded, to be condemned to death (#20, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Minister of War, on the sentences to be given to the mutineers (#21, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Minister of War, on Panoff's declaration (#22, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Minister of Foreign Affairs, on the search in the Consulate of Rumania, a rebel officer was hidden there (#23, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to Captain Drandarevski in Silistra, nominating the military court, 1887 February 22 (#24, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to Captain Drandarevski, Silistra, on sending by boat two canons and troops to Roussé, 1887 April 24 (#25, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Minister of War, on the description of the mutiny in Roussé (#26, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff, on the new details about the mutiny (copy of the cable sent to the Regents) (#27, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Commander of the 2nd Regiment of Artillery, 1887 February 24, Shoumen, on sending a battery to Tarnovo (#28, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to same Commander, on the same subject, 1887 February 25 (#29, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Commander Captain Tepavski, Silistra to Major Racho Petroff in Roussé, on the description of the mutiny in Silistra (letter from Benderev to Captain Krasteff,) 1886 November 22 (#30, in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from the Regents, Stanboulov, Lt. Colonel Mutkuroff and G. Jivkoff to Major Racho Petroff, prohibiting him to receive any letters from the Russian Consul or to meet him ("the process of the mutineers should be ended in an hour time") (#31, in Bulgarian)
  - The sentence, condemning the mutineers, signed by Major Racho Petroff, 1887 February 20 (#32, in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from the Military Attorney in Roussé to the Commander in Chief of the Eastern Department, 1887 February 22 (#33)
  - A letter from the Commander of the Garrison in Tarnovo, to the Commander in Chief of the Eastern Department, 1887 February 23,on a robbery effected by 5 soldiers (#34)
  - A report from the Military Attorney in Roussé to the Commander in Chief of the Eastern Department, announcing the exact time for the execution of the condemned mutineers, 1887 February 23 (#35)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Commander of the Fleet at Roussé to send "Golubtchik" to Svichtov and Vidin with 120 marines (#36, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable to the same Commander to send "Opit" to Silistra in order to bring back marines, 1887 February 24 (#37, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A report from the Commander of the Port Company in Roussé to the Commander of the Fleet, 1887 February 24 - a full report on the mutiny (#38, original in Bulgarian
  - Similar report from Captain Anghelov (#39, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Report from Sub-Lieutenant Markoff to the Commander in Chief of the Eastern Department, 1887 February 25, presenting the sentence against the mutineers (#40, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - Report from the Commander in Razgrad, Captain Kissiakoff to the Commander in Chief of the Eastern Department, requesting two months leave, joint two medical certificates (#41, original in Bulgarian)
  - Order from Major Racho Petroff to Captain Kosaroff, appointing the last Chief of the Artillery Arsenal in Roussé, 1887 February 26 (#42, original in Bulgarian)
  - A report from Captain Kissiakov, Razgrad, to Major Racho Petroff, demanding instructions, 1887 February 26 (#43, original in Bulgarian)
  - Two demands from prisoners condemned to death to Major Racho Petroff to change their sentences (Fidantzef and Bochnakoff,) written in the Prison of Roussé on 1887 February 27 (#44, original in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff to the Commander of the Shoumen Garrison to inquire the state of alarm happened in Shoumen on February 18 and 19, and its connection with the mutiny in Roussé ans Silistra (#45, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A report from the Commander of the Fleet in Roussé to Major Racho Petroff, 1887 March 7 (#46, original in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from Major Racho Petroff to Captain Ouvaliev, appointing him Commander of the 2nd Regiment of Artillery, 1887 March 6 (#47, in Bulgarian)
  - A report from Captain Kessiakoff, Razgradto Major Racho Petroff, on financial subject, 1887 March 5 (#48, original in Bulgarian)
  - A letter from Major Racho Petroff to the Commander of the troops in Silistra, 1887 March 6, answering his demand for leave (#49, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A report from the military attorney in Roussé to Major Racho Petroff, 1887 March 2, changing the death sentence of Fidantzeff and Boshnakoff to 15 years in prison, following an order from Major Racho Petroff. A report of the Commandant on same matter, 1887 March 4 (#50, original in Bulgarian)
  - A report from the Military Commendant in Roussé to Major Racho Petroff, on the execution of the sentence concerning some sergeants, 1887 March 4 (#51, original in Bulgarian)
  - Captain Tepavski demands a leave of seven days, 1887, March 6. Major Racho Petroff's answer: "only after finishing the process against the mutiny" (#52, original in Bulgarian)
  - A report from the Military attorney in Roussé, on the execution of the sentence against the rebelled sergeant-majors, 1887 March 3 (#53, original in Bulgarian)
  - A report from the Military prosecutor to Major Racho Petroff, on an accident which happened during the process of the mutineers, 1887 March 5 (#54, original in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from Major Racho Petroff, to Captain Tzontcheff in Shoumen,on the inquiry of the mutiny there, 1887 March 11 (#55, manuscript in Bulgarian)
  - A cable from the Commander of the Regiment in Shoumen to Major Racho Petroff, 1887 March 23, on the situation of the Regiment's doctor (#56, Manuscript in Bulgarian)